Bourrillion: The Multiset API
adds only five methods
on top of what's already
in the collection interface.
And it, you know--
These are methods
that are designed to do
the sorts of things that you
typically do
when you use a Multiset.
So very common thing,
you want to know
how many occurrences
of a particular element
are in there.
So that method's
called "count."
You may want to add--
oops.
You may want to add
a whole bunch of occurrences
at the same time
or remove a bunch of occurrences
at the same time.
And you may also want
to directly, you know, say,
okay, I don't know how many
I'm adding or removing.
I just want you to make
the count this value.
So in Multiset terminology,
if you add the letter A
to your Multiset three times,
we call that
"three occurrences of A."
And the total number
of occurrences of A
is called "the count of A."
Those are the terms
we adopted.
We could also say frequency
and multiplicity,
but we just don't use those
in our--in this doc.
So you could directly set
the count to a new value
or you could say conditionally
set the count to a new value
only if its current count
is the old value.
Once you have these methods,
then these are actually suitable
for use
in concurrent applications.
You're able--
these provide you the ability
to do atomic operations
without needing a special
concurrent Multiset interface
because in this case,
the base interface
simply has all the methods
that you need.
In retrospect, java.util.map
might have also had
all of those methods,
but that was
a long time ago.
We learned things
since then.
Uh...that's--
Okay, and then we have--
Oh, my god, we have six
implementations of Multiset
in our library,
although, you know, most of them
share a lot of code.
First and foremost
is ImmutableMultiset.
We also have Immutables for all
of our own collection types.
And then, you know,
if you want--
The main question is,
since Multiset tracks duplicate,
you know,
the count of occurrences
of a particular element,
you have to think about
how do you want it to decide
whether element A and element B
are really the same?
If you want it to use
hashCode and equals,
that's a HashMultiset.
If you want it
to use a comparator,
that's TreeMultiset,
and that also has the effect
of sorting all the values.
And if your elements are Enums,
you may as well
use EnumMultiset
because that'll be faster
and simpler.
And there's
the ConcurrentMultiset
I told you about.
Any questions about Multisets?
Okay. Yes.
man: You couldn't transform
an immutable to a mutable?
Bourrillion:
You can always--
The question is can you
transform a immutable...
man: Or make a copy
thereof?
Bourrillion:
into a mutable?
And that's simply
a copy operation.
So every--
every mutable collection
is usually going to have
a copy constructor
or a static factory method that
serves as a copy constructor.
In the JDK collections,
there are constructors
that take collection.
In our library, we have static
methods that take iterable,
but the concept is the same.
man:
Right, um...
just to follow up,
in a--if you have--
man: Just put it
up to your mouth.
man: Oh,
if you have a...
the immutable case,
once you've created a collection
that is immutable to begin with,
you can exploit some extra
data structuring underneath,
perhaps, to take advantage
of the fact
that there will be
no more insertion to it.
Bourrillion:
Right.
man: So do you do anything--
can you talk about that?
Bourrillion: So, um,
in the immutable collections,
it's a very--
you know, we know up front
what the exact size is gonna be
so we can size
the data structure,
and we don't have to have
any of that logic
for providing
for resize operations at all.
The other thing
that's nice is
in certain cases
like an immutable set,
we can actually--
the first time
that someone calculates
the hashCode of the set--
This is getting
a little esoteric,
because most people
don't call hashCode
on their sets very often,
but the hashCode of a set
is defined
as the sum of the hashCodes
of all the elements.
Once we do that once, we can
just simply cache that result
and then we don't have to keep
doing it over and over.
And that means if we're testing
two immutable sets for equality,
we can first check
their hashCodes
and it's really, really fast
if they're not equal.
man: What about also
the queries--
the individual queries
into a set
or an immutable set
or an immutable map?
You can optimize
the data structure inside to say
each query itself
can be pretty fast.
Bourrillion: Well, I suppose
what we should do is--
like, when you get out of here,
you could--
you could go look
at our code and--
or if we have a laptop,
we can look at it together
after the talk,
and we'll sort of look at how--
I don't know
if I could talk through it
off the top of my head.
But certainly--
there's certainly a lot of
corners that we're able to cut
because of
the immutability situation.
man: What about testing
with JSTL?
'Cause, like, I see, like,
with the count you mentioned,
you didn't do a get count
and things like that,
and that's gonna require
a key to look up.
Has any testing
been done there?
If I was to--
Bourrillion:
I don't know what JSTL is.
man: Okay.
Bourrillion: Do you want
to tell us about it or is it--
[laughter]
We can talk later.
I'm sorry.
Bad me.
Gentleman in the front row
is beginning to become
something of a pest.
[laughter]
Josh: I'll shut up
if you want.
Bourrillion:
No, that's okay.
Josh: But I wanted to make
a very minor point,
which is that what you referred
to as "copy constructor."
I apologize. I really think
I used the term wrong
in the first edition
of "Effective Java."
So, in the second edition
of "Effective Java,"
I call them
"conversion constructors."
That's it.
Bourrillion:
Conversion contructors.
Josh: Because you're picking
the, you know, type
of the thing
that you're creating.
Bourrillion:
Okay, I'm gonna try to get
a little bit faster,
but not much.
So now we move on
from Multisets to Multimaps.
So how many times
have you ended up
writing code like this,
where you have a map
from some key
to some collection of values,
and you're trying
to basically store
a many-to-many relationship?
In this case
we have salespeople and sales.
And we want to build up a map
that will let us find
all of the sales corresponding
to a particular salesperson.
And this is the current way
of doing it
without the benefit
of libraries like ours.
Each time that you make a new
sale that needs to be added,
you've got to find out
whether you already have a list
stored in this map for that key,
and if you do,
you can just add to it,
and if you don't, you've got to
create one and add it yourself.
So this is pretty much
an idiom,
and, you know, once
you've encountered it once,
you can sort of do the same
thing from time to time,
and it's--you know,
it's not that bad.
But let's look further.
Would you rather do this?
In this case, we create
what we call a Multimap.
Okay, we're not the only ones
who call it a Multimap.
You can look it up
on Wikipedia.
Everyone calls it a Multimap.
From salesperson to sale--
and this time the implementation
of our method is simply put.
That's all we have to do,
and under the covers, it will do
all this ugly stuff for us.
The--the benefits
of this are pretty clear
and they're similar
to the benefits of the Multiset.
The code has become a lot
less verbose and bug prone.
It also offers--
this is another--
you know, returning to what
I was emphasizing before,
it means that as you start
to need more and more
complicated things,
the library is ready
to give you those things.
You don't have to go
and write all that code
to do those things again.
And here's an exam--
this is not an example.
Okay, first, I'm gonna--
yes, question.
man: This is one-in-many,
not many-to-many.
Bourrillion:
Uh...
man: One salesman
has multiple--
Bourrillion: It's many-to-many
in the sense--
Okay, it's not
bidirectional many-to-many,
but the same key
can have multiple values,
and the same value can have
multiple keys as before.
So you could say that--
in this terminology,
you could say a regular map
is many-to-one, right?
Because you could have distinct
keys with the same value.
But it's not bidirectional.
You can't navigate it backward
in that direction.
Am I making any sense?
Okay.
Suffice it to say,
here's what a Multimap is.
It's a collection of key-value
pairs, just like a map,
except that keys
don't have to be unique
in this collection
of key-value pairs.
So you can have A=1, A=2
and then B=3,
and then you could have a bunch
of values for C.
And now I see a lot of hands up,
so let's start over here.
Do you want to find
a microphone?
man: So in all the examples
that you have shown,
you've basically been using
the factory intent
to create, uh,
any of your collections.
But you are not using
the constructors anywhere.
Is there any
particular reason?
Bourrillion:
Yes.
Yes, constructors
are basically pains in the--
can I say asses?
I think I just did.
They're--constructors really
are a big pain.
The main reason--
the most
immediately apparent reason
is that Java C
does not have type inference
for the generic-type parameters
of a constructor.
So, as long
as you're calling constructors,
you always have to do
really ugly stuff like this.
All these type parameters
on your type variable here
have to be repeated
word for word
on the constructor.
There is absolutely
nothing else
that you could put
in between these angle brackets.
It has to be exactly this
or it won't compile.
Yet Java C
makes you specify it anyway.
man: But do you have the public
constructors in your--
Bourrillion:
Do we have public constructors?
We do have public
no-argument constructors,
but we don't go and provide all
the same convenient overloads
in the constructors
as we do in the static--
in--in fact, if you look in--
I think it's section one
of "Effective Java,"
that says prefer or consider
static factory methods.
And there's
a lot of advantages in there
to static factory methods
that we agree with.
Other question?
Or maybe--okay.
man:
Is there any provision
for going multiple levels deep
on those lists?
'Cause I sometimes
had to create,
like, you know,
a list of a list of something.
Bourrillion: I don't think
we have anything
that specifically
addresses that right now--
like, basically a map
from a key
to a map from another key
to a value
and sort of multilevel things
like that or lists of lists.
man: Well, yeah,
like a map from a key
to a list of lists
of something.
Bourrillion: Oh, okay,
no, I don't think we have
anything like that
right now.
We just sort of work in order
of, you know, the volume
of code that needs the method.
No, I don't think
we've gotten around to that yet.
So, in this case--
Yeah, all right.
man: Just one question
about Multimaps.
What will return method get
if no--any elements
will follow...
Bourrillion:
Oh, yeah, so any time--
man: Null or empty
collection.
Bourrillion: Very good question,
and I believe that question
has a right answer
and a wrong answer.
"Multimap.get(key) returns
a modifiable Collection view
of the values associated
with that key."
Therefore,
if there are no values,
you get an empty collection.
We're not
just gonna return null.
And in fact,
this is a live view.
So even if it's empty, you can
insert an element into it,
and that will cause
the corresponding entry
to appear in the Multimap.
So this is a very--
a very powerful thing
about Multimap,
is it supports
lots of view collections
that allow you
to look at the data
in many different ways,
and this is one of them.
So sometimes
you want to think
of your Multimap
in these sort of terms.
So, for example, like,
if you do web programming,
you know that URL
query strings
can look like this,
like I've described.
You can have the same key
appearing multiple times.
And so we have a URI--
or URL class
that actually uses Multimap
to represent
the query parameters.
But sometimes you would actually
rather think of it
this way below,
where you have a single key
and then the collection of all
the values that map to it.
So if you want to look
at it this way,
we have an asMap view
that you call on the Multimap,
and now you can look at it
in this way.
There are a few subtypes
of Multimaps.
So right here,
I said that get on a key
returns you a view
of all the values
that correspond to that key.
And that view is a collection,
but different Multimaps
will have different behavior
to that collection.
So the names that we're using
for these types
are ListMultimap
and SetMultimap,
because in ListMultimap,
the collection of values
corresponding to a key
implements the list interface.
And in SetMultimap,
it implements the set interface.
So you get the behaviors
that this implies.
For example,
in a SetMultimap,
you're never gonna have
duplicate entries.
You couldn't have
duplicate entries,
because then
the value collection
corresponding to a key
would not be a set anymore.
So we have ListMultimap,
SetMultimap,
and SortedSetMultimap.
And there could be others.
At this point,
you might be thinking
it sort of sounds
like we've come full circle,
and you just
basically have a map
from key
to a collection of values,
so you could almost have just
stuck with the original code.
But now I'm about
to kick it up a notch.
Let's go back to our
"salesperson and sale" example.
Now we want to find
the largest sale.
That's it.
We had to write all that code.
So we have this data structure
that maps salespersons to sales.
And we just want to find
the biggest one.
And look at what we had to do.
You know, this should make
your blood boil, right?
When you see this,
you should think, you know--
You know how some people
are always saying,
"There ought to be a law"?
So when you see this,
you should think,
"There ought to be a library."
And you should expect
to find that library
somewhere, hopefully.
And in this case,
it's our library.
What did we have to do?
We had to loop
through each of the lists
that were stored in the map.
We have to find the max sale
in that list
and then compare it
to our previous max sale
and, you know, close all
these loops and then return it.
Or we could've built up
a temporary collection
and for each list
put the biggest
in the temporary collection
and then call max
on the temporary collection.
But what would this look like
with a Multimap?
It looks like that.
One line of code.
The reason it's so simple
is that the Multimap
has all kinds
of view collections
that let you view the data
in different ways.
And when you can view data
as a collection,
then you can take advantage
of all the many utilities
that have been already built
to deal with collections.
So collections.max
expects the collections,
so we use
the Multimap.values view,
which feeds it all the values
across all the keys
and just pulls out
the largest one.
So...
man:
Where's the comparator?
Bourrillion:
Where's the comparator defined?
man:
To be fair.
Bourrillion:
It could be anything, though.
So the comparator is the same
in both examples.
So I use it
in this example here
and I use it in this example.
So, you know, what it probably
does is it takes a sale,
and it calls the .get charge
method on that sale,
and then it does the same thing
to the other sale
and compares
the charge values.
But it doesn't--
it's not really relevant
to the A-versus-B comparison.
man: Oh, I see. I'm sorry.
I withdraw the question.
Bourrillion:
Okay.
[laughter]
Cool.
Whew.
He withdrew the question.
man: If only
I could go back in time.
Bourrillion:
Okay.
So, yeah, the point of this
is we love view collections.
They're very, very powerful.
They allow you to magnify,
to multiply the total number
of different things you can do.
Is there a question?
Yes.
Microphone.
man: So now that you got
your biggest sale,
how do you get to the salesman
who made that sale?
Bourrillion: Well, this example
isn't doing that.
man: Okay.
[laughter]
Bourrillion: So I--
what did you say,
you withdrew
the question?
I withdraw the answer.
[laughter]
Different slide,
different day.
man: So couldn't you
just use the same technique
with a different comparator
and, you know, view the thing--
taking the appropriate view,
which preserves--
Bourrillion: Yes.
Here's what we would do.
Instead of taking
the value's view,
we would take
the entry's view.
Entry's is a view
containing Map.Entry objects,
which are the same type
that you have in a regular map,
because all they do is they
consist of key and value.
And you'd use the--you'd find
the max entry from that,
and then you could navigate
from there to both the--
Thank you.
You saved me.
I un-withdraw my answer.
[man speaking indistinctly]
man: Please take
the mike.
man: Right? It blows up
the entire set of values
into one list.
Bourrillion: Okay, I can also
just repeat the question.
That's fine, too.
man: It just expands the whole
set of values into one list.
So if you've got a map
that's got lots of values in it,
it can use up
a lot of memory.
Bourrillion:
No, actually.
man: No?
Bourrillion:
So this value
is simply returning to you
a view upon all those values.
It's not actually copying
all of that data
into another structure.
It's simply
a custom implementation.
And this is why we have Jared,
Jared--
'cause he masterminded doing
this kind of crazy stuff.
man: This sounds
much cooler than I thought.
Bourrillion: Yes,
it's--that's--you know...
[laughter]
If there's one takeaway
I would like everyone to have
from this presentation,
could you repeat that?
[laughter]
man: I guess...
Bourrillion:
I think it was,
"It's much cooler
than I thought."
man: It sounds much cooler
than I thought.
Bourrillion: That's good.
That's how I feel.
Okay, so I was supposed
to pick up the speed a little.
Most of the methods
on Multimap
are really just very parallel
to the same methods on Map.
And if you can imagine
going back in time
with all this being
in the JDK,
these could've implemented
a common interface
because they behave
exactly the same.
Other ones
look a little bit different.
For example,
the get method--
you know, instead
of returning a V,
it returns
a collection of V.
And we have a couple
of different remove methods.
One to remove
a particular entry
and another to remove
all of the values for an entry
and so on and so forth.
I'm gonna gloss over that
a little bit.
And there's
a few new things too.
It's very full-featured.
And we have
five implementations...
so far.
Okay, that's it
for Multimaps.
I'm going to start now doing
more of a rapid fire
over some of the other types,
because they're a little bit
less ubiquitously--
a little less popular
than the first two, I guess.
Question.
man:
Concurrent Multimap--
Bourrillion: Oh, yeah,
so Concurrent Multimap
is in experimental stage
right now.
We're still going back and forth
on a few of the design issues.
We're sort of letting it--
letting it build up some usages
internally first.
And we may end up promoting it
into the external library.
Hopefully.
[man speaking indistinctly]
I'm sorry.
Yeah, theoretically it works,
and it appears to work
in practice.
So a BiMap, also known
as a unique-value map,
is just a map where all
the values are unique.
So this is good for--
first of all, if you just want
the extra checking,
you know,
if you're building up a map
and you know the values
are supposed to be unique,
go ahead and use a BiMap,
and that way it will blow up if,
you know,
if those aren't unique,
at the expense
of the extra memory
that a BiMap does require.
The coolest thing
about a BiMap is that
because the values are unique,
it has an inverse view,
which is also
another instance of BiMap.
Can view that same BiMap
in either direction.
And if you take the inverse
of the inverse,
you get right back
where you started again.
So I'm sure that many times
you've had data
that you populated
in a forward Map
and a backward Map
separately.
You can keep doing that
if you want,
or you can just let us do it
for you.
That's basically what--
what this interface amounts to.
We'll take care of, you know,
making absolutely sure
that those two stay in sync,
even in the face
of all kinds of mutation
that they could be undergoing.
And there's a few
implementations of this too.
ReferenceMap--
this is not a new type.
It implements ConcurrentMap,
which is an existing type.
And, uh,
you know,
if you have never used
weak references
or soft references,
first of all,
you're lucky.
I mean, like,
that's great
if you never have to deal
with them.
You're--I kind of wish
I was in those shoes.
But if you--if you
aren't familiar with them,
you can take a snooze.
If you are familiar with them,
then you know about weak HashMap
in the JDK.
It's supports weak keys
with, what, strong values?
Martin, Josh?
But there's really
nine different combinations
that you could want.
You might want any
of strong references,
weak references,
or soft references
for your keys
and strong, soft, or weak
for your values.
So there are
nine possible combinations.
Of course, if your combination
is strong and strong,
then you wouldn't be using
this anyway.
You would just be using
a regular HashMap.
In addition to this,
it fully implements
the ConcurrentMap interface,
and it is a fully
concurrent data structure.
And it has to be,
because cleanup
of these stale references
is happening in the GC thread.
So as long as we were following
that strategy anyway,
we went ahead and exposed
this concurrent behavior fully
in the API to you.
Josh.
Josh: One last question,
I promise.
So those idiots
who wrote weak HashMap
really got the identity
semantics all wrong.
It uses equality
rather than identity,
but it only makes sense
when equality and identity
are one and the same.
So did you smart folks,
you know, fix this up
in any way?
[Bourrillion laughs]
Bourrillion: Yes,
so rather than going to idiots,
I went to Crazy Bob.
And so Crazy Bob
implemented this.
And, yes,
he does the right thing.
The--with weak references
and soft references,
it's always
identity semantics.
With strong references,
currently it's always
equality semantics,
but we have considered the idea
of adding a fourth option,
which is strong with identity.
So you would have soft, weak,
and then strong identity
and strong...
the other one.
But we haven't done that.
I felt compelled to point out
that it is not yet
as fast as it could be.
If the code ever
becomes imported into the JDK,
such that it has access to some
of the package private internals
of java.util,
we can make it faster.
We could also make it faster
if we were willing to do
some really, really ugly stuff
with the code.
And we might have to resort
to that one day,
but for now, we're using it
in production,
and it's fast enough,
so we're--we're not worried.
man: You have a lot
of computers to run it on.
Bourrillion:
Yes, we do.
We do have a couple computers
to run it on.
That's true.
So this--this is sort of unique
among our collections,
in that if you don't--
if you need to do what it does,
it's just really, really hard
to do it any other way.
man: Could you give us,
like, one example
of, you know,
where this gets used?
Bourrillion:
Okay, so it's used a lot--
it's used a lot for caching.
Say that you have, like,
a customer object,
and you want to cache in memory
this whole list of transactions,
but what you want is for when
that customer gets garbage--
You want that customer--
you don't want to prevent
that customer
from being garbage collected.
And if you just use strong
references in your cache,
now you have--you're gonna hold
on to this customer forever.
Actually, as a business,
we do want to hold on
to our customers forever.
But in our code, we like them
to get cleaned up.
So the weak reference will--will
not prevent garbage collection,
and when garbage collection
does happen,
the entry will just get removed
from the Map automatically.
Okay.
Switching gears,
we have a class called Ordering.
I mean, it's starting to get
to the part of the talk
where I'm just gonna skip from
random thing to random thing.
In the JDK, you probably know
the interface comparator.
And it's used
for comparing things
and deciding which one's
less than the other
or if they're equal.
And this is an interface
with one method,
and so it's very easy
to implement,
but it's a pain to use.
Usually
there's a trade-off there,
and the designers, rightly so,
decided to focus
on ease of implementation,
because you tend to implement
these things a lot.
What we have done
is created a class
which we've had
to call Ordering,
which really is a richer version
of the comparator.
And what you do is you take
your existing comparator--
So here's a comparator
that exists in the JDK,
String.CASE_INSENSITIVE_ORDER.
It's a comparator
that compares strings,
ignoring case.
And you can call
Ordering.forComparator,
and you get
the ordering instance
that corresponds
to that same comparator.
Now, this ordering
also implements comparator.
So you can use it
as comparator,
but it has a whole bunch of--
Oh, of tasty methods
on it also,
like min, max, isIncreasing,
sortedCopy of an iterable.
You can also call
.reverse on it.
Now you have another ordering
that is just the reverse
semantics to the original one.
So this
is a slightly more OO way
to provide
all of these utilities.
Instead of just having a long
list of static methods
that take, you know,
these iterables
and comparators passed in,
we let you turn that comparator
into a richer version of itself.
We let you upgrade
your comparator
to a super comparator.
And then you can do
all this fun stuff
much more naturally and
object-oriented in--in a way.
I'm gonna move on to covering
some of our static utilities.
Static factory methods, we--
has them.
We do this
for all of our collections.
We don't--
We touched on this earlier.
We don't want you to have
to type all of this garbage
in your code.
Garbage belongs
in the garbage collector,
not in your code.
So things like this
are just tremendously sad,
and it's--I mean,
it's--it's more sad
to the people who worked
on generics and the language
than anybody else.
You know, it's like,
there's real weeping
that happens over this.
I've seen it.
And we'd very much like this
to be fixed
in the language
in the future
so that you did not have
to redundantly specify
all this stuff.
But our library
is about what you can do today,
so we make sure to provide you
a static method.
It just happens that in Java,
static methods
have excellent type inference,
and so you don't have to go
and repeat those parameters,
except in a minority
of edge cases.
In fact, this is so nice
that we also provide
this whole litany
of static factory methods
for JDK collections as well.
And we put them in classes
called Lists, Sets, and Maps.
These are actually by far
the most popular thing
in our whole library.
They're
one-liner implementations.
They do absolutely nothing,
but they make
your code cleaner,
and that's
really important to us.
We want your code to be clean.
We want it to be very readable.
And this is something
that if you,
for whatever reason,
don't use our library,
but you are using Java 5,
you should at least open up
these files
and paste all that source code
into some class in your own--
in your own project
so that you can call
these methods,
because it's just--you know,
this stuff is just such noise.
But them in its--that in itself
might not be enough for you
to motivate you
to use our entire library,
but you can at least steal
that stuff from it.
I wanted to talk
for a few minutes
about working
with iterators and iterables.
This is another big area
of support in our library.
It's something that we--
we tend to treat iterators
and iterables
as first-class citizens
a little more
than the JDK library does.
And it's a constant source
of friction
between me
and my office mate here.
In our opinion, collection
is a really good abstraction
to be working at when all
of your data is in memory.
If all of your data
is not in memory,
like you're, you know, reading
it from a file or whatnot
and you want to make
a single pass through it,
you can implement collection,
and, you know,
that can be all right sometimes.
But it tends to be
more cumbersome
than is always necessary,
and when you're all done
with all that cumbersome stuff,
you're gonna end up
with a collection
that may be
sort of badly behaved.
People may take that collection
and just called that size on it,
and they may not realize
that that's gonna cause
your collection to go and slurp
the entire,
you know, data stream
out of a BigTable
or what have you.
So we tend to focus
on iterator and iterable.
If--if that's all our method
needs you to give us,
that's all we ask for.
We don't make you pass us
a collection.
As well, we also have classes
called iterators and iterables
that are full
of useful utilities
for working
with these things.
So these
are parallel structure.
You know, the exact same methods
appear in iterators class
that take iterator parameters
and iterables class
that take iterable parameters,
except for the ones that don't
make sense in one or the other.
And they
let you do things, like,
I've omitted some
of the generics from here
because it was too verbose
for my slides.
But you can transform.
You can--you can pass
all the elements of one iterable
through a function
to get another iterable.
You can filter
based on a predicate
and a whole bunch of--of other
methods with predicates,
like find, any, all,
and so forth.
You can concatenate
an iterable of iterables.
So, if you have
a whole bunch--
So we were talking
about lists of lists.
If you have a list of lists
or something like that
and you want to view them all
as a flattened list,
you can use this method.
You can cycle--
you can get an iterable
that cycles over
a source iterable infinitely.
Things like that.
The thing that all these methods
have in common
is that they're absolutely
as lazy as possible...
because I wrote them, and I'm
absolutely as lazy as possible.
[light laughter]
So they will never access
the backing iterator or iterable
until they have to.
So this will be familiar
to many devotees of functional
programming languages.
It's a really good thing--
When you have
a lot of data to process,
you can set up a whole--
you know, you can concatenate
these things
and then filter them
and transform them,
and then only
as you start to access the data
will it actually turn
all of these gears
and actually go through
and read all of the input.
It needs to be said
that having interfaces
called function
and predicate
and having methods
to transform and filter them
based on them,
does not exactly make Java
into a wonderful
functional programming language.
So if you love
functional programming,
and a lot of people do
for very good reasons,
and you'd love to be able
to do FP in Java,
you can--you can do it,
but it's gonna be ugly.
And I would say
in many of the cases
where people
have started using these APIs,
in some cases,
it's a net win,
and in some cases,
it's actually a net loss.
Sometimes their code ends up
just being more confusing
and filled with more
generic-type parameters
in inner classes and jumbled
than it was before.
Java, as a language right now,
isn't really set up
to do FP that well.
The reason
that these methods exist
is because sometimes
they're just what you need.
And when they are just what you
need, you should use them.
But if you do use them,
take a--take a look
when you're all done
if you really like the way
that your code came out,
'cause you may find that,
in some cases,
you would've been better off
just doing things
the old-fashioned way.
And that's my spiel
about that.
Questions?
Nobody wants to take me
to task about FP?
Yeah.
man: There's a class,
like a navigable.
The collection--is the iterable,
like, similar?
Bourrillion: No,
so iterable is--
sits at the very base of the--
of the inheritance tree.
It is even more general
than collection.
So iterable has only one method
called "iterator,"
which will let you get
an iterator.
And then you have collections,
sets, sorted sets,
and navigable set
is way down here.
It's a very large API
for dealing with sorted data
and, you know, navigating it
in both directions
and finding the head set
and the tail set
and all kinds
of really great stuff.
We're really looking forward
to supporting navigable set
and navigable Map in our API,
which we will do once we make
our big Java 6 transition.
Other stuff--
Yeah.
man: One thing that--I don't
know if it's ever been fixed,
but has always seemed like
a really big conundrum to me,
which was that anybody
in this world could divide--
design an interface like Set
and not have their
most basic operations in it,
like Intersection
and Difference,
which I think Rogue Wave does,
but the JDK doesn't.
And I never could figure out
how anybody could do that.
It just puzzles me.
[laughter]
Bourrillion:
Who can we blame?
Who can we lynch?
Josh: So, you know,
basically it's one-liners
to get those things,
right?
Remove all and retain all
give you precisely that,
but you have the choice as to
whether you want to do them
destructively
or nondestructively.
So, you know, we gave you
slightly more
general operations.
That said, I acknowledge
that, you know, the names
are a little harder
to understand,
and I certainly believe that
when you're designing an API,
you know, you must understand
your audience.
You must produce an API
that is pleasant to use,
and I think, perhaps,
we could've done better there.
That said, you know,
I-I think that on balance,
we made a lot
of good decisions,
and I think that, you know,
the past 11 years have shown
that it is an API that has
withstood the test of time,
you know,
albeit it has faults.
Bourrillion: And I want to point
out that if you want union
and intersection
and difference methods,
we have them in our library.
[laughter]
So you can use them.
Josh hates them. No.
Josh: No, no,
I don't hate them at all.
And in fact, I'm surprised
that we didn't have them
in collections.
Bourrillion: It's actually
a little nontrivial
to decide
how to implement them
because you don't want
to simply choose for the user
what type of implementation
you're gonna put
the results into,
because the user
might have SortedSets,
or he might have
Linked HashSets,
or EnumSets,
or whatever.
And you don't want to just
arbitrarily say,
"We're gonna use Linked HashSet
for our result type."
So our--our union
and intersection
and difference methods
are implemented as views.
So when you call methods
on them,
they simply call
to the underlying methods.
And then there's a method
you can say, "Copy into."
And then you can tell it
exactly what kind of collection
you want to copy it into.
That's sort of in common
throughout our whole libraries.
We try never to choose
implementation for you
unless it's in a method called
new Hash Set, you know?
Then we give you a HashSet.
But instead, we try to, like,
return you in iterable
and let you copy it into
the type that you want it to be,
things like that.
This is the slide
that I'm gonna just skip.
This is the stuff we're not
telling you about.
We're not telling you about all
of our forwarding collections,
constrained collections,
precondition check methods,
union/intersection/difference--
but we did tell you
about those--
Multimaps.index
and Maps.uniqueindex,
ClassToInstanceMap,
AbstractIterator,
PeekingIterator,
and all kinds of other stuff.
So that stuff exists too.
Not telling you about it.
And we're just about done,
but I wanted to put one slide
on here to brag--
[laughs]
to tell you about how we test
all of this stuff,
because we have
over 25,000 unit tests
for this library.
A fact
which I'm very proud of.
And we owe this fact
to a couple of Googlers.
I have their names down there--
Chris Povirk and George.
And Chris Povirk and George
built this framework that--
basically for every different
collection implementation
that we have,
we sort of use this API to tell
it the features
that that collection has.
Does it allow null values?
Does it have comparator order
or arbitrary order or whatever?
And we, you know,
fill in an interface
where we actually
create the thing,
and we send it
off to this thing,
and it returns us
a JUnit TestSuite
that'll have, like,
115 methods in it,
or tests in it.
And it's pulling those from--
we have these big test files
full of all these methods
that are annotated,
and it matches up
these features
with the annotations
and methods,
and it constructs just
the right TestSuite
that verifies every last
unbelievably nitty-gritty thing
about the collection.
In fact, there are several
JDK collections
that do not pass
all of our tests.
And ours do.
Now, this is not to say
that JDK collections suck.
This is to say
that we're talking
about really anal-retentive
little things here.
And in every case,
there are bugs filed already
against the JDK,
but it hasn't, you know,
hasn't been super-high priority
to get them fixed yet.
But hopefully that gives you
an idea of the--
our level of commitment
to really honoring the letter
of our specification
very, very tightly.
And this framework
will be open-sourced
at some point soon,
and then if you write
your own collections,
you can actually use this to
test your own collections too.
That's it.
We finally made it to the end.
Andreas.
Andreas: Yeah, a question
about the previous slide.
Bourrillion:
Yes.
Andreas:
You guys are saying
you're, like, being very
particular about the test.
Why are you using
a string literal then?
Bourrillion:
String literal?
Andreas: I mean,
for the, like, name.
I mean, why not actually...
Bourrillion:
Oh, for the name.
Andreas:
Yeah, for the name.
'Cause, like, for the test,
'cause then that's another place
somebody can screw up.
Bourrillion:
This right here?
Andreas: Yeah.
Bourrillion:
So this is just decoration.
This is just so that
when your TestSuite is running,
it's showing you
what it's doing.
That's all.
Andreas: Okay.
Bourrillion: Yeah, and then
these things here
are actually Enums--
these general purpose,
allows null values,
and so forth.
Andreas:
Okay, cool.
Bourrillion: Okay.
Questions?
man: So is the intention
to put this
through the JCP
at some point?
Bourrillion: Do one of you want
to answer this,
or should I take a crack?
Josh: Yes.
[laughter]
Bourrillion:
There you go.
So it's really--
The JCP is not necessarily
the ideal form
to do real
forward-thinking development.
It's a lot easier
to just develop all this stuff
under the auspices
of an open-source project,
get people using it,
and then when things look
pretty firm,
and you've battle-tested them,
and you've figured out
what things should be named,
then the hope
is that we'll start a JSR
or do whatever process
will exist at that time
to--to try to put some
of the stuff in the JDK.
Martin.
Martin: So when something
goes into the JDK,
it--it's kind of like
it's frozen forever, right?
Code is really, really,
really hard to change
once it's in there, so...
And the--when you--
So I used to work at Sun,
and when you work at Sun,
it's--you have to work--
you know, you have to try to get
it right the first time.
And human beings
aren't very good
at getting it right
the first time.
So I think that the model
that's being used here,
where code
is actually being run,
it's being used by real people
in production,
and then you want to put it
in the JDK.
I think that's the right order
to do things in.
Bourrillion:
That brings up a point
that I wanted to--to explain,
which is, you know,
why is this library
being developed at Google,
and why is it
coming from Google?
Part of it is
because, you know,
we have some really,
really good people
who I've been able to ask all
of my questions.
I-I-I basically typify
the--the expression
of standing
on the shoulders of giants,
because everything I do,
I just ask,
like, enough,
you know, experts
and try to put it all together
in my head
and figure out what to do.
But the other part is ju--
we simply have
an environment at Google
that is very, very conducive
to the development
of libraries like this.
It's really very unique.
We have
a very aggressive attitude
towards sharing code here.
If I have, like,
a performance improvement
or an API improvement that
I want to make to a library,
I can get that change made
and actually out in production
in every Google service
on their next push.
It's sort of a system--
it sounds kind of mind-blowing
when you think about it,
that I can actually cause
changes that don't have to wait
for the sign-off of every
individual project first.
But this situation has led
to a really unique ability
to, you know, write code,
get it used, see how it works.
If I need to rename something,
I literally open up
all of the Java code
in Google in IntelliJ,
and I hit Shift-F6,
and I modify that code
and everybody's client code
at the same time.
That's literally
what I do so...
And together with that,
we have no shortage
of really wonderful,
opinionated engineers,
who join my mailing lists,
and we discuss all
of these things, and through--
you know, when we get a really
heated debate going on,
that's when we really know that
we're--we're gonna hit
on something really good
out of that.
So it's sort of like--
I don't know
how we could've developed this
anywhere else, but at Google,
and I just wanted to...
say that.
I think you had your hand up
first, in the front row.
man:
Yes, so I was gonna ask
about whether
you were influenced
by the Apache Jakarta Commons
or whatever,
but now I want to ask you,
when you do those huge
global refactorings
like rename or whatever,
do you find that the next day
anybody has changed
anything back?
Bourrillion:
Nope.
If they did, their code--
their build would break.
man: Okay. So then maybe
the Apache question.
Bourrillion: Okay.
So we were not really influenced
by the Apache library.
We were aware that it existed,
but because Google
adopted Java 5 in generics
very early on, it was very--
and we went through
and we generified all
of our code, like, really fast.
Again, I used IntelliJ.
I loaded up
a big swath of code,
and I hit, you know,
Alt-Shift-F12 or whatever,
and it generified
all the code.
So once we crossed
that Rubicon,
then--then generics
were very important to us,
and there was no officially
available generified version
of the Apache library
at that time.
When we noticed that and we also
noticed that the Apache library
takes a different approach
to us in many ways,
when it comes to adhering to
the letter of the specifications
of the interfaces that they
implement from the JDK.
So we're very,
very hard core
about following those interfaces
as tightly as we can,
and their library,
for valid reasons,
decides to depart,
you know--
I don't want to say it's
a totally dumb thing to do,
but they've chosen to depart
from those specifications
in certain ways
and just try to flag it
in their java.doc
as saying, "Violation."
Um, I decide that--
or we decided that
when, um, code implements
an interface
but it doesn't adhere
to the letter
of what that interface says,
then your code is gonna
be harder for people to learn.
They have more stuff that they
have to keep in their head.
The more edge cases
they have to think about.
And if you just get religious
about it as much as possible,
then you've just made
everyone's lives easier.
So because of that, you know,
we just sort of have
an independent evolution
from that library.
We've never really, like,
you know, reviewed that library
to get ideas of what to do.
Our ideas come directly
from what actual Googlers
are trying to do
in their projects.
We look at their code
and we say, oh,
you had to write 50 lines
to do this.
Let's--let's write a library
that you can use.
man: Uh, this is kind of
a two-part question.
The first part is, uh,
how many people did it take
to write those 25,000,
uh, unit tests?
Bourrillion: So the 25,000
unit tests
weren't written by people,
right?
They're written by this
framework that spits them out.
Right? So in terms of actual
number of test methods
that we've written, maybe it's
only like 2,000 or something.
I don't know. And then it's
recombining those in many ways.
And it's doing it--
it's doing so in such a way
that everything gets created as
an independent JUnit test case
so that when one fails,
it doesn't cause a whole huge
thing to fail.
It just pinpoints exactly
what the failures were.
And that's what blows
those numbers up.
man: Oh, okay.
And the second part
of the question was, um,
if, um, it takes, uh,
all this, uh, experience
and--and expertise of the
world's top Java programmers
to write these--what
accomplishes this task here,
which is really, uh, relatively
simple at least on the surface--
I mean, you know,
you're not--
we're not doing
rocket science here.
We're doing the kind of stuff
that we learned in,
you know, data structures
classes and what like that.
Um, then what--what chance do
the rest of us poor mortals have
of writing a bug-free code
when we're actually writing
a real application
that's really complicated
like maybe putting a lander
on Mars or something like that?
Bourrillion: Um,
so the question is, uh,
so I've alluded
to the difficulty
of writing this library or how
much work we've spent on it.
And the question is sort of,
if it's--
if it was that hard
for us to write the library...
man: Yeah. This is a fairly
simple task compared to, um...
Bourrillion: Which is a fairly--
writing the library?
man: Yeah, I mean,
a library is a relatively
constrained environment.
It's not--it's a pretty
small task compared to...
Bourrillion: I remember
when I used to think so.
man: Right.
Bourrillion: That would be
before I spent
the last three years
of my life writing libraries.
man: Right. But just think
of a large application that has,
uh, you know, uh, really life--
life-threatening consequences
or, you know, safety concerns
and things like that,
uh, with--without--doesn't have
the kind of resources even
that you can really bear down
on such a small--
you--you're using a fairly large
amount of resources
at least intellectually
on a fairly small problem,
whereas the rest of us a lot
of times probably have to deal
with a bigger problem
with less resources.
I'm wondering how we can
actually write code that's--
that's reliable.
Bourrillion: Our approach,
you know, the approach
that, you know, Jared and I
and, uh, the rest of us
who've worked on this
have been taking
is to try to build up
from the bottom level,
higher and higher level,
utilities that do more
of the work for you,
that cause you to have to write
less code,
that cause you to have to test
and test--we test the hell
out of our things,
so that, uh, that--
do I want to say that rising
tide lifts all boats?
I just said it.
Um, so that's our angle
on trying to make
your job easier.
Other people are working
on possible language changes.
Other people work on tools
and so forth.
We do it through libraries.
Uh, it's, you know,
I-I kind of want to address
the idea
that writing the library
is--is easy or simple
because it's not.
I don't know how else
to describe why.
But it's been very
challenging.
Um...so...
man: Sorry for that
distraction.
Bourrillion:
That's all right.
Next question.
Uh, Josh?
Josh: Well, can I just add
a little to your--
your previous answer?
Bourrillion:
Yes, please.
Josh: So writing libraries
is much harder than it looks.
I think the guy who, well,
is reputed to have said it best
is, uh, Thelonious Monk.
Although he wasn't actually
talking about libraries.
Um, he said simple
ain't easy.
He didn't actually say that.
It turns out what he really
said was, "them simple chords
ain't so easy to play now."
But it's the same idea.
The thing about a library is
if you did it right,
it looks
and feels incredibly simple.
And achieving that turns out
to be incredibly difficult.
And it's worth it because
of the economies of scale.
You write these things once
and they're used by millions
of people for tens of years.
And that's why it's worth
putting so much effort
into libraries, you know,
because you have this tremendous
economy of scale.
And you can't afford to apply,
uh, that much effort
to the system
that you're building.
You know, does that mean
you--you can't make
a mission critical system
that works?
No, it doesn't mean that.
But the thing about
your system is
it doesn't have millions
of programmers
are gonna confronted
with actually using those APIs.
So if the APIs are a little bit
more difficult to use,
it's not the end
of the world.
If his are a little bit
more difficult to use, you know,
multiply the pain
by the millions of programmers
who are gonna use them
over the years
that they're gonna be
using them.
And--and furthermore,
if you can make them
just a tiny bit faster,
they're in people's
inner loop.
This is inner loop code.
So, you know, all the time
we talk about
don't prematurely optimize.
In this case, you know,
we actually have to optimize.
And it's not premature.
We know upfront
this is inner loop code.
Bourrillion: Anyone else?
man: Time for two more
questions.
I just wanted to get queued up
to do the raffle.
Just as a--
just as a segue though,
you mentioned several times
about IntelliJ IDEA.
The one thing we're raffling
off tonight is a free license
to IntelliJ IDEA so...
Bourrillion: I would be lost
without it.
man: Cool.
man: I just wanted to...
man: People that worked
on a project?
man: Oh, I'm sorry.
This is everyone who registered
in advance.
When we do the raffle,
the spinner is actually
written in JavaFX.
Woo-hoo.
Bourrillion: The--the list
of people who have contributed
meaningfully to our project
would probably have
just about that many names
on it though.
Although it's a long
tail effect.
But because of the open, uh,
sort of development process
that we have
in the mailing lists
that anyone can join
and participate in any
of our discussions
and every line of code
that we write gets,
you know,
emailed out and discussed
to death on these lists.
So I can't even properly
thank all the people
that I--that I should
be thanking.
Uh, but certainly, uh,
Josh has been our biggest
spiritual advisor.
And, uh, Jared,
who may have slipped out,
has written--
oh, there's Jared--
has written most of the code.
And, uh, and Jesse's been
a huge help--back there.
And, uh, some other people
at other offices
who aren't able to be here.
Did I just snub anyone?
man: Can--I just wanted
to make my comment
that I very much appreciate
your work
especially with the java.util
collections library.
And I know that you put
a lot of work into it.
And I use it all the time.
And I value it very highly.
And this stuff looks fantastic.
So, uh, so thank you.
Bourrillion: Thank you.
[applause]
You wouldn't believe
how infrequently
people bother to say things
like that.
So thank you.
man: Yes. Thank you very much,
Kevin.
Uh, so, I-I actually did not
do one of the announcements
at the beginning.
Um, there was someone here
from QCon,
but they weren't able
to stay.
So the QCon conference
coming up in November--
Uh, I guess I should have said
that my favorite conference
locally is--in September--
is--is the Rich Web
Experience.
But my favorite con--
well, I can't even say that.
But it is a good conference.
I haven't been to QCon.
But if you look
at the speaker list,
it's just really impressive.
So I have some, um,
handouts here
that have a promotion code
for $100 off.
If you think you're at all
interested
or if you know someone
who might be, please take one.
Uh, and next meeting,
the--the JUG user meeting,
uh, on the 18th
with Rod Johnson,
she'll be coming back since she
wasn't able to do it tonight
and we'll be raffling off
one free pass
to that conference.
And it's, uh,
I don't know what it goes for,
but that--that's at least
in excess
of $500 conference
so, uh...
And besides, it's Rod Johnson,
so you gotta come back.
[laughs]
So let's just do
the raffle now
for the IntelliJ IDEA
license.
Um, you have to be here
to win.
And so we'll keep going.
And if you really won't use it,
just say so,
and we'll spin again.
But you really should use it
if you haven't been already.
man: Put these
on the back table.
man: Okay. Great.
man: These'll be
on the back table
if you're interested.
man: And--and so
we're spinning.
[laughs]
man: Who wrote this?
man: Uh, Jim Weaver wrote
the original code.
We tweaked it a little--
actually, Kevin tweaked it
a little bit.
man: It's me. Oh!
man: And the winner
is Oswald!
Where are you, Oswald?
Did he leave?
He was here.
man: Oh, we gotta give it
to him.
man: Oh, no, you have to be
present to win
even though we know
the person.
man: Oswald's a good guy.
man: He's actually someone
who's been a great supporter
of the group.
But I'll just have to--
I'll have to run again.
He's gonna be bummed.
He probably already has
a license actually.
man: I bet I can get him one
anyway.
[laughter]
man: Stephen!
Are you here, Stephen?
All right,
another long-time regular.
Cool. So we'll just
have to get your email
and we'll--we send your name
and email to them
and then they set you up.
Okay, so if you come back
on the 18th,
we'll have another license--
you'll have another, like,
1 in 100 odds chance
to win a license
to IntelliJ.
[laughs]
All right. Thank you.
Thank you for coming.