Wang: Hi. My name's David.
I'm from the Google Wave team.
I work on
the Live Concurrent Editing
that you've probably seen
in the last demo.
So how do we actually do it?
So the way we do it
is use a technology called
operational transformation.
It's been a very active
academic research area
for quite a while now,
about ten years.
And we've actually taken
that algorithm
and extended it to provide you
the live concurrent editing
that you're so used to now.
How does this all work?
So let me show you
with an example.
So imagine we had a client...
and we had a server...
and it all started
with the same state--
A, B, C and D.
Now, imagine the client
wanted to insert some character
between C and D.
So he now inserts, let's say, X
between the character C and D.
And the server actually wanted
to delete the character B.
So now he ends up
with the state A, C, and D.
Now, these happen concurrently.
So how do they communicate
that they've done these things
on both sides?
So what they do
is they send the action,
which we call operation
on the wire.
So the client sends an insert X
at position 0, 1, 2, and 3.
And the server
sends the operation
delete character B
at position 0 and 1.
So now when the other side
gets the message,
they could choose to blindly
execute it if they wanted to.
But what would happen
if you actually blindly execute
an operation?
So if the server executed
the operation from a client,
insert the X blindly,
you'd end up with the state
A, C, D, and X.
But that's clearly not what
the client wants to do.
So what we have to do
is go through a process
called transformation.
So what happens
is that the server
takes the client operation
and transforms against
its own operation,
and it results in
a new operation
where he inserts char X,
now at position 2
because he has to subtract
a position
for its own deleted character.
And now the server
applies the operation,
and you end up with the state
A, C, X, and D.
The client, on the other hand,
does the exact same
transformation.
However, in this case,
it just happens
the operation gets transformed
into the exact same operation.
So the client now ends up
with B deleted
with A, C, X, and D.
So as you can see,
now both the client
and the server
ends in the exact same state
even though they have done
the operation concurrently
at different locations.
So why is this liveliness
important?
So let's take an analogy,
let's say.
Imagine you and your friend
walked in a cafe,
and you were just having a
conversation between each other.
When was the last time
you closed off your ears
and said to your friend,
"Wait, finish your sentence
and tell me about it
afterwards"?
Well, this is clearly what
we experience today
on instant messaging
where someone else
types a message,
and you wait for them
to finish.
You wait and wait and wait.
But you don't really wait
in the cafe
for your friend
to finish talking
before you listen
to him, do you?
It would really break
the flow of conversation.
Now, by making things live
and concurrent,
you now have a very
engaging conversation
just like how you would
actually talk to a person
where you can converse
very quickly.
One of the important things
we have done in Google Wave
is that we've chosen to use a
client and server architecture.
It's a very interesting
academic area
to use this complete client
system without any servers.
However, we've purposely chosen
client/server architecture
because it allows us to scout
the large number of clients
without complicating the system.
So imagine in this case
we had a client, client one,
connecting to a server,
and another client
connecting to the server.
They now interact
to the server...
by communicating
and using the server
as a point of relay.
So what does that buy you?
What this buys you is that,
number one,
there is a single system
which holds the source of truth.
So even if the clients crash
or go offline for a long time,
there's one place where
you can go and fetch a document.
The other important thing
is that by modifying operational
transformations slightly,
we're able to have a very
efficient single source of truth
which is the server.
What modification we've done
is that we've changed
the operational transformation
by forcing the client...
wait for the server
to acknowledge this operation
that the client has just sent.
What this means is that
the client always stays
on the server's operational
transformation path.
This allows the server
to keep a single history
of operations
without having to keep
a mirror of the client state
for each client
that's connected.
What this means is that now
for as many clients
that's connected to the server,
there's only a single copy
of the document on the server.
What's even more important
is that because there is
a single stream of operation
that is now happening
on the server--
so in this case,
there's a little
operation that happens here,
there's a little operation
that happens here--
you can now do
the single playback.
What this means is that
you can actually see
how things happened.
So you've probably seen
in Lars's demo
where he was able to look
into the past
and see what someone else
edited.
But how did he do that?
He did this by simply
going back to the server
and asked the server,
"Please give me the operations
that you executed
in coarse digestible amounts
that make sense to me."
And in this case,
for example,
a client operation
can be played back
in a single step.
Another client operation
can be played back
in another step.
I think this is a very cool
piece of technology.
It allows very live
and concurrent communication,
just like how people
sit in the same room
and communicate
in an engaging conversation.
And so I hope this technology
will be useful to you too.