Kroeger: So good afternoon.
My name is Robert Kroeger,
and I'm gonna talk
to you about
caching patterns for building
offline web applications.
Um, where did my slide go?
There we go.
Um, this is, uh--
This is the sort of
design pattern we use
underneath the mobile
GMAIL application
that you might have seen
on the iPhone or the Android.
So of course,
first question is
why build a mobile
web application at all,
you know, instead of, say,
a native application that runs
directly on the phone?
Web applications,
they tend to have
two large advantages that
Vic alluded to this morning
in the keynote.
First off,
phones are pretty small.
I mean, our phone is,
you know--
it's better than
the Unix work station
I had on my desk
ten years ago.
But it's still really tiny
compared to our data center.
You just can't run the kinds
of apps on the phone
that you might like to.
Another problem
with the phone--
with building native apps--
is that it's hard
to distribute phones.
So much easier to distribute
a web app.
There's no app store
approval process.
You know what
I'm talking about.
You'll get to launch
on the schedule you pick.
You don't have to wait
for someone else to decide
that it's okay to have your code
on their device.
There's no mobile provider
in the way.
And you can update frequently
and fix bugs.
Maybe even weekly.
Maybe even daily,
like we have had to do lately.
Um, the problem is that
sometimes
building a mobile web app
is kind of slow.
You know, I mean,
the server has a nice,
fat connection to the internet.
But the phone has
a little, skinny,
not-so-fat connection
to the internet
over EDGE or 3G.
And there's two problems
to this connection.
The first is it can be
very high latency.
It can take seconds to establish
a radio connection.
And the other big problem
with this is it comes and goes.
I don't know if you ever tried
web browsing on MUNI
or on any other
public transit system,
but sometimes
it's going along great,
and then all of a sudden
it's, like, oop,
no signal, no signal.
And this is king of
disappointing,
especially if you application is
synchronously connected
to a server over the pipe.
So how can we fix this?
We fix this,
at least in mobile GMAIL,
with caching.
We wanted to split the--
split the UI
from being dependent,
synchronously,
on a connection to the server.
And we did this by inserting
a big green cache--
that's a pun,
and it's kinds bad--I'm sorry--
between the actual UI
and the rest of the system.
So you see that at the bottom
of the lower diagram
where we've placed this cache
that's connected to the UI.
And so as a result,
UI updates needed
to repaint the user interface,
they come out of the cache,
they go to the UI.
And obviously the user makes
modifications to the,
you know, the state
of the application.
That gets written
into the cache.
And we have this nice
little loop
that's entirely local
from the user interface
to the cache and back.
And then, of course,
the cache--
Asynchronous [indistinct]
user's interaction
with the system
pushes these changes
to the server,
and, of course,
responses come...oops--
sorry--
come back from the server
and get written to the cache.
And the cache has to
merge all this together.
And so we've divided
our application up
into a part that's local
and synchronous,
and a part that is asynchronous
and involves
the connection to that work.
So let's look inside
the green box--
the cache pattern itself.
So it has four basic
data flows on the left side.
The red ones are the data flows
to the user interface
that are intended to be
reasonably fast and immediate.
And on the right we have
the sort of asynchronous,
arbitrary latency interactions
with the server.
But, you know, we need a place
to keep all the data
that we're storing
in this cache.
And so, you know,
where do we keep it?
We want some kind of
persistent storage
in the browser itself.
And that brings us
to structured storage.
So HTML 5 and Gears
they're both--
they both add some kind
of structured storage
to the browser.
And structured storage is
really great
for implementing this cache.
It's a largely complete
SQL database.
And it's all
on the mobile device,
so you don't have to go off
over the network to fetch it.
And we can actually
get to it
even if we don't have
a network connection at all.
Um...
And you know, it has
two really great properties.
First off is it's persistent.
If the browser crashes
or is terminated
by the operating system
because you ran out of memory,
it's still all there.
All your edits stay there
in the persistent structured
storage.
And, of course,
it also implements
the sort of standard database
ACD properties.
You know, atomic
and consistent and durable,
and all that goodness
that they taught us
long ago in computer science
class.
And that's also really helpful
in the case of, "Hey, look.
The operating system
just tossed the browser."
So that way you don't lose
your edits.
Now, there's a problem,
and the problem is that
HTML 5 and Gears have
really quite radically different
programming models
for how to get access
to the structured store.
Gears has a synchronous
interface to the database.
So what does that mean?
It means that you have
the nice little
JavaScript thread
running your code.
And when you want to make a call
with Gears Call
to fetch data
out of the database--
You can make a function call
into Gears.
That's the sort of red
database action code there
in the top diagram.
And then the Gears code
processes.
And then it returns
in the standard kind of,
you know, UNIX-system-y call
kind of way
to the calling JavaScript
thread.
HTML 5 is different.
You know,
it starts out the same.
The JavaScript code
makes a call
to the, um--
to an underlying,
or a SQL thread,
that runs database actions.
But that sort of runs separately
and independently.
And it--it doesn't return data
to the JavaScript.
Instead it calls back
into the JavaScript
at some arbitrary point later.
Now, this is sometimes
harder to program,
but it also has the advantage
that other JavaScript,
like button clicks,
can happen in the meantime.
So we can kind of sum up
this difference
in this nice little table here.
On the Android device,
we get SQL databases,
we get via Gears.
So it's a synchronous
programming model.
And on the iPhone we get
HTML 5 databases
that are asynchronous.
And so in, you know,
that little red problem area,
we can't have structured storage
on both platforms the same way
that have different
programming models--it's a pain.
So we have a solution
for this.
It's something we call the
Web Storage Portability Layer,
which is a long descriptive
name, and I know it's too long.
And I'm gonna frequently say
WSPL instead.
Um, WSPL,
you write your cache,
or any other kind of structured
storage web application,
to a single common
programming model.
And on HTML 5 devices,
the nice little wrapper
translates that
into HTML 5 calls.
And on Gears we emulate the
asynchronous programming model
with a Gears worker
that runs asynchronously
to the mainline thread
and does all the database--
all the synchronous
database actions using Gears.
And this is, uh--
You know, as of yesterday,
this is now open-sourced
from code.google.com/p/
webstorageportabilitylayer.
And I encourage you
to go have a look.
And eventually the material
in these slides,
at least some of it,
will get added to that site.
So thanks to this WSPL layer,
we have solved the whole
"where to keep the data" that
we want to put in our cache.
We keep it in some kind of
arbitrary WSPL-wrapped database
that sits underneath
our web application.
And you'll see
there's two arrows
going into and out of
the WSPL layer in the picture.
And this is because
WSPL has to provide
an asynchronous programming
model
to be compatible
with HTML 5.
And so the one arrow going into
the WSPL layer,
those are calls
from the cache.
And then there's callbacks.
That's the other arrow.
So the underlying kind
of mechanism is taken care of.
We talked about, sort of,
the cache structure.
And this is very much
the architectural pattern
that is found in mobile GMAIL.
Albeit with some tweaks
and differences.
We can talk about
the cache pattern in detail.
So it's kind of busy,
so sorry.
But you know, there's--
It's not that--
It's pretty complicated
in some ways.
The first thing that you'll see
is I've doubled up
all the arrows
because, you know,
the interface to the WSPL
has just, you know,
one call one way,
and then a call the other way.
And so all the other interfaces
on this cache structure
have to be bi-directional
as well.
So I've also given
each of these calls names.
And that's because
there's a demo app
that comes with the WSPL
distribution
that I called "Simple Notes"
that actually uses these names
in the code.
So you take, for example,
"Get" values--
that is a call from the UI--
into the cache to get content.
And then there's a callback--
a value callback--
logically enough,
that delivers the content
from the cache
back to the user interface.
So what about this
Simple Notes thing?
So the simple point
of Simple Notes is essentially
just to make all this
more concrete,
and to demonstrate the use
of WSPL,
and to provide sort
of a concrete,
somewhat simplified
"getting started" implementation
of the cache
that people are free to use.
You can extend it
any way you want.
First off, Simple Notes
is really a toy application.
And, because, you know,
I had too many years
of college math.
The server side is an exercise
for the audience.
And the first person
who writes it gets some swag.
And you should go
to the app engine talk
and learn how.
Now...
[chuckles]
with that little Tom Sawyer
moment out of the way,
Simple Notes has
three basic pages.
They're essentially just
different divs.
And they're hidden and displayed
by the appropriate
CSS modification.
There's a "list notes" page.
There's a "show
and entire note" page.
And then, of course, and "edit
or create a new note" page.
And Simple Notes itself
is really not very useful,
but the cache component is
pretty much complete
and is a good starting point
for building
an arbitrary cached application.
So there's some important
design aspects
to how you you actually
implement a cache
of the kind that
we're talking about here.
And they all sort of come out
of the hardware literature.
Because, you know, people have
been building caches
and hardware for years.
The first thing is
we need to know--
we need to be able
to determine
if a requested entity is
in the cache or not.
So we need some kind of
hit determination mechanism.
In Simple Notes we keep
a contiguous range of notes
in the cache at all times.
So it's pretty easy to decide
if we have a note in the cache.
If it's between two--
You know, if its index is
between a pair of numbers, yay.
Otherwise,
we have to go fetch it.
We also have to have
some refresh mechanism.
We have to have some way
to know when to fetch content.
New notes from the server,
and how to add them
to the, um...to the cache.
And what to do about, of course,
getting rid of the notes
we don't need--
the eviction process.
And finally, we need
a coherency mechanism.
We have to figure out,
in the client,
how to join server changes
and user changes together
in the cache
such that you don't lose
the user changes.
And--
And they don't like that.
So now some more details.
So first off,
Simple Notes is implemented
as two separate
database tables.
You'll see it's pretty standard
SQL code there.
Also you'll notice that
we use the WSPL statement object
to wrap our SQL strings.
This is just
a convenience thing
to simplify
parameter substitution
so that it works both
on Gears and HTML 5.
And also, we have some
statements down at the bottom.
Select statements to go
to the database
and find out
what are the end points
of the range of notes
that are in the cache.
And so this is what would get--
These two statements
would get creation statements
to build a database.
And, of course, finding
the end points of the cache
happens at the setup
of the application.
We chose to separate
the cache's backing store
into these two
separate tables.
Into a right buffer table
and a cash notes table
in order to divide state
fro actions.
The state is, you know,
sort of the model
that the user's seeing
and interacting with.
And the actions are things
that we need to preserve
because we're sending them
to the server,
or merging them with refreshes
that have come from the server.
And by putting these
in two different tables,
it provides a nice
simplification
of the architecture.
And this sort of arrangement
of a table of actions
and a state table
corresponds
to the hardware notion
of a write-through cache, which
was kind of one of the simpler
"read, modify, write"
hardware caches
that one could build.
Here's some code.
And it's, well,
it's essentially just a setup.
And this is all in distribution,
so if you down load it,
you can have a look at this.
It creates tables,
and it loads some triggers.
And we'll talk about
the triggers shortly.
And it determines, as I said,
what's already in the database.
The last two "selects."
So one of the things
that you should know about
this piece of code
is the use of "execute all."
This is a convenience function
we added in WSPL.
So you can pass an array
of statements to the library
and say,
"just go do all these."
As opposed to, in HTML 5,
just out of the box,
for every single
separate SQL statement,
you have to have a call
to HTML 5
to fire the correct piece
of SQL,
and then a callback handler.
And this just
made life simpler.
Also notice that
asynchrony comes up even here.
We don't know if
we've actually completed
the creation of the tables
and the addition of--
and the addition
of the triggers, et cetera,
until some callback is fired
from inside
of the WSPL library.
And so we can't tell the UI
that we're done
without a callback
that we provide in the,
you know,
the callback argument.
So let's talk about
the sort of data flows
through the cache
in a little more detail.
Um, this is the case
of the "get values."
Your sort of basic
give me something
out of the cache query,
and get a response.
And so the basic idea is
the UI will call into the cache
to obtain, say, a note,
or a list of notes.
And there's a whole sequence
of WSPL calls,
or HTML 5 calls,
as the case may be,
that are required
to implement that.
See that at the bottom.
We have to first create
a transaction,
and then,
inside of the transaction,
callback.
We have to dispatch
some SQL statements
and then get the results.
And then, finally, once we've
accumulated all the results--
with accumulated results,
of course--
we forward the response--
the complete, entire
result set--
back to the UI for display.
The implementation looks
a bit like this.
This is just, essentially,
a wrapper
that fires off
the right kind of, sort of,
a larger helper method.
And...
There's two things
wrapped here.
First is, you know,
get notes--a list of notes.
And the other one is get
just one note.
And get one note is
much simpler.
It only has to obtain
one thing.
And so we just kind of
skipped over it.
So the code looks like this,
pretty much.
So it starts...on...
It starts about there, really.
Starts in the middle.
All the stuff above
is the definition
of callback functions.
And then the first thing
that the mainline code does
is it creates the transaction,
like I said.
And then that transaction is
the "in transaction,
get notes" function
that you see second
from the top
in the list of callback
functions.
And then,
inside that transaction,
we run the "list cache notes"
SQL statement,
which, of course,
just does a select
over all the notes
in the database,
and returns that.
And then that gets
accumulated
in the "accumulate results"
callback.
So the...
inside the transaction,
the SQL statement's sent
to the WSPL library.
And then the callbacks aggregate
in the "array notes,"
and then the transaction ends.
So this little color diagram
at the bottom
shows you the time sequence.
We have the start
of the function in red.
And then the transaction
boundary is defined
by the sort of yellow region.
And we can control
the transaction boundary
by explicitly creating
the transaction,
and providing a function to run
inside of that transaction.
And then that first function
that's run inside
of our transaction,
it dispatches the SQL
that we want to have execute.
And then the callback also runs
inside of the transaction,
and could, in theory, dispatch
yet more SQL, et cetera.
And then finally,
when all the functions
that were invoked
with a valid transaction object
have finished,
then the transaction is closed,
and the changes, if any,
are committed
to the database.
So there was a little piece
of code in there
where we determined if
something's in the cache or not.
As I said earlier,
it's really very simple.
In Simple Notes we just have
a list of notes,
and we store their
end-point IDs.
And if you're in the range,
yay.
And if you're not
in the range,
we must go fetch the note
from the server--
or range of notes
from the server.
The next piece of the cache is
handling user changes.
So this is the case where
the user makes some chan--
uh, modification.
And we want to put that
into the right buffer,
and then apply that result to
the actual state of the cache.
And we actually do
the application of the change
from the right buffer
to the cache state
with a trigger.
And then finally acknowledge
the change to the UI.
And triggers are a very,
very useful function
in SQL light
and HTML 5 and Gears.
They really help improve
performance
and simplify development.
And as a result of the use
of triggers,
the actual JavaScript code for
making a change to the cache--
to a user UI change
is very simple.
All it does is--
A little piece of SQL
that inserts an action
into the right buffer.
Now, why use triggers...
for a complicated update,
like updating a cache state
from an entry
in the right buffer?
Triggers help avoid
ping-ponging,
which can be very expensive.
Rather than having the case
where, you see at the top,
where we run a little bit
of JavaScript,
start a transaction,
fire off some SQL...
The database does some stuff.
The database calls back.
The JavaScript does some stuff.
You know, executes some more
JavaScript.
Rather than have that sequence
of back and forth,
instead, we have one
little piece of JavaScript
that starts the process by,
you know,
writing to the right buffer.
And then the trigger does
all the work.
The transaction's shorter.
There's no need to go
back and forth
between the threads.
And it just runs vastly--
It runs vastly faster.
It especially runs faster
if you're emulating this model
of the two threads
with Gears workers.
And this also--
By making your transaction
shorter,
you can work around a number
of somewhat nasty bugs
in the HTML implementations
currently shipping.
Um...
so here's the actual
trigger code for Simple Notes.
The triggers for mobile GMAIL
are much more complicated
because you can do more
to your mail
than just add a note
consisting of note text
and a subject.
But the basic idea is the same.
You know, we have something
in the action queue,
and copy it into the cache.
Uh, the cache state, per se.
There's two statements here.
The first just does the copy,
and the second updates some
state bits in the action queue
to track that we've actually
done the copy
so we don't do it
over and over again.
Um, it's worth noting...
that--well, it's worth noting
that the trigger's the only way
to do a whole bunch
of SQL statements
without this ping-pong process.
It's the nicest way if you have
a whole bunch of SQL,
and you just want it to run
without worrying
about its result--
it's the nicest way
to do that.
Makes it--
It's the easiest way to write.
The next sort of main flow
in the cache itself
is insert update.
And insert update is perhaps
the most complicated flow
through the cache.
It's the case where
we've received--
The application--
the mobile app--
has received content
from the server.
And we have to combine
that content
with the existing contents
of the cache
and any changes
the user has made to the cache
that haven't yet reached
the server.
So the basic idea is
that it all starts
as a result of the callback
on XHR.
That's the insert update
in the top right.
And then we do some work
to put all the changes
into the cache.
Once again, we use a trigger
to replay actions
that have not yet reached
the server
against the changes made
by the server on the cache.
And finally, if this was all
in response to a cache miss,
we have to send
the new updated results
back to the UI.
Because the UI will have been
waiting the entire time
for this round trip
to the server
if the desired value
is not actually cached.
Now, it could have been doing
useful things in the meantime,
but it wouldn't have
been able to show
whatever that requested
entity was.
So here's a sample of a code.
Um...
[clears throat]
the basic idea is that we start
by creating
all the statements necessary--
at the top,
that's the four loop--
to write the server's updates
to the cache.
And this code presumes
that the changes are sent
as a JSON-encoded array.
That's just, you know,
an array of little--
of JavaScript objects.
The next thing we do is
we remove--
that's the eviction statement--
remove all of the notes
in the cache
that are not part
of the desired request.
And we have a very simple
eviction policy in Simple Notes.
We maintain a range of,
you know, I through J of notes.
And everything outside of that,
we just throw it away
and assume the server has
kept it.
The next thing we have to do
is we have to, um...
mark the contents
of the right buffer--
the actions--to reapply,
so they can get reapplied
to what we've just put
into the cache.
Because these series of updates
have possibly destroyed
user changes that haven't
reached the server.
We need to update,
at this point,
where the little arrow points.
The notion of what is
in the cache.
And it's important to do this
at the start of the transaction,
as opposed anywhere else,
so that any subsequent
transactions
will see correct state.
And JavaScript code that is
not yet inside of a transaction
will also see what state--
It will find in the database
when it's allowed to have
its transaction run.
These kinds of--
Well, I don't know,
I used to like drawing
diagrams
to try to plot out these things.
It can be a bit tricky
with the whole
asynchronous callback model
figuring out where
you actually are
with regards to updates
in JavaScript,
and updates in SQL.
Because there's no
sort of--
They can happen overlapped.
Finally, if this particular
update is a result
of a cache miss,
we call back to the UI
delivering the content
that we received
from the server.
Finally, we have
this last case.
which is where "get values"
is handling a cache miss.
And in this case, you know,
we will have had
a "get values" call
enter the cache.
And it needs to do--
It needs to obtain
from the cache
all of the requests.
It should replay--
It should send to the server
prior to sending a query.
And then, only after
it's done that,
it sends this aggregate bundle
of updates plus queries
all to a server as one
so that the server can apply,
prior to generating
the query result,
all of the as yet unseen
user actions.
And this should be starting
to look pretty familiar by now--
this code.
It's the same basic structure.
We begin at the top
by accumulating
a bunch of records that we need
to send to the server.
And we mark the state
of the records
that we are sending
to the server.
And the right buffer is
being in flight.
And then we send those
plus the query upstream
to the server via XHR.
So this diagram should hopefully
make this
a little bit more clear
about how we're maintaining
consistency.
The gray cloud is obviously
the network.
And the green box is
the contents of the right buffer
over time.
And way out there
at the left,
the user has made, prior to
the start of this diagram,
one change that is stored
in the cache as "change 1."
And they then do something
that causes a cache miss,
and so the UI--
The cache is gonna fire off
a "fetch from server" call.
And what does it do?
Well, it obtains update one,
and it suffixes that
with the query--
the desired object
that's wanted.
It sends it out to the server.
Well, let's say it fails.
The XHR times out.
You're offline.
And you need it to authenticate.
You lost your cookies.
Something bad happened.
In that case,
the app change response
from the XHR comes back.
And we mark in the failure
callback that, hey, we tried.
We sent the action to bed,
and we told the UI we couldn't
satisfy the request.
Uh, more time passes.
The user keeps using
the application.
They make another change.
This would be change 2,
via the applied UI change there.
So now there's change 1
that has not reached the server.
And change 2 that, well,
we haven't sent it
to the server yet,
but we don't know
if it would fail.
But maybe by this point,
the user's gone online.
And so they once again call
"fetch from server"
to fetch more content.
And once again we need to
extract from the write buffer
changes 1 and 2.
And then append to that
the desired query, "Q."
And that all goes to the server
as one big bundle.
And this time it succeeds.
And so the server responds
positively
with the desired
query result,
and acknowledges it's received
changes 1 and 2.
But in the meantime--
because it takes time
for things to reach the server,
and for the server
to do things--
the user's made
another change: change 3.
So if we replace
the cache contents
with the result of the query
that we have just sent
the server,
we will lose change 3.
And that's the point
of the reapplication,
is that first we update
the response--
that's the "Q" response there
that you see there
in the diagram--
by insert update.
And then we reapply the change 3
via the trigger
that I already discussed
to make sure that now
the state of the cache is
whatever was on the server
at time "Q," plus change 3.
So some miscellaneous tidbits
that are worth talking out.
First, I've assumed that
all the content going
up and back to the server
is always some kind
of JSON-encoded content.
Always sent by XHR post.
If you're using app cache
in your application as well,
it almost has to be post.
It probably can't beget.
Or put--I guess put is post.
Um, and then, you know,
for all the missing bits
I haven't talked about,
most of them are
in the distribution and will...
and should run.
The asynchronous programming
model that you see
in HTML 5 databases,
and you see in WSPL
for the same reason,
can be kind of difficult
sometimes
because it sort of changes
the order of your code.
It makes the order
it runs in
not necessarily even remotely
like the order it's written in.
So it's a good idea
to have planned out
what you think the order
of the code is--
its execution order.
And to invest in
some good logging frameworks
for your code before developing
with HTML 5.
So you know what
is happening when.
It can be very hard
to deal with.
Another important tidbit
with HTML 5 is
triggers are--they really--
they really make life
so much easier.
The SQL in the trigger,
well it runs
in the order it's written in.
So it's easy to figure out
what it's doing
in comparison to
the JavaScript callbacks.
And it also makes it
a lot faster to develop.
You can make some very rich,
pervasive,
and well-structured changes
to your database
pretty easily in SQL.
Of course,
you can also damage it.
So you know, my advice it
use triggers as much as you can.
They make life easier.
The other thing is that
they run on a separate thread
from the UI thread.
And so the fact that
a trigger is progressing
does not block the execution
of the UI thread
where the user is clicking,
and you're rendering the results
of changes the users made
onto the screen.
And that helps keep
the application responsive.
And finally, I've sort of
glossed over
some sort of tricky problems
in the Simple Notes
example code.
In particular,
at least on a mobile device,
the database isn't actually fast
enough to serve as the model
in a model-view-controller
architecture
for your application.
You need some kind
of memory-based model
that is served from the cache.
It's also the case that
the database size limits,
at least on current-generation
iPhones,
is such that you probably
will find that
your model in memory,
and your model in database,
will be both the same size.
Which has some opportunities
and some additional issues
having to do with
making sure that
you evict the right stuff.
I mean, in theory,
you could keep different things
in cache and in RAM model,
and sort of double up how much
you have available
to show to the user.
Finally, Simple Notes makes--
does too much data traffic.
When you refresh your cache
in Simple Notes,
we just grab all the notes
over again
that are within
the desired range.
It's clearly not
the right way to do things.
The right way to do things
would be to grab
only those notes that have
actually been modified
on the server.
And one way to do that
might be to add
some kind of date stamp
to the tables,
and then sent that
to the server.
And then the server would say,
"Ah, yes,
these ones have changed,"
and only send those back.
Now, that would require,
as part of servicing cache miss,
a trip to the database
before you can send the query
to the server.
And that means that
it takes longer
to service the cache miss,
and that increases latency
if the cache is empty.
So these are kind of--
Lots of interesting
design trade-offs
to be worked out.
So in summary, the cache pattern
is workable in real products.
It's actually what we're using
in GMAIL for mobile.
The WSDL library is
also workable.
It's actually, if you've used
you iPhone with GMAIL,
this code is live and shipping--
WSDL.
So it does actually work.
And it does provide a workable
local storage solution
across both iPhone and Android
platform devices.
So that's--that's--
We're at the end
of the presentation.
I invite questions.
You can go to the microphones,
please, if you have questions.
Or we can use the moderator
to find it.
Oops. Wrong window.
Um...
Questions?
man: Hi. Uh, how well
the database is secured?
Kroeger: Pardon me?
man: The security
of the database.
Kroeger: The security
of the database?
man: Uh-huh.
Kroeger: So the security
of the database is,
in our case, left in the hands
of the browser.
The browser enforces
domain-level access
in the sense that
if your app is served
from www.google.com,
only other apps served
from that domain
are allowed to access
the database.
Obviously if you have
shell access
to the device in question,
the security doesn't exist.
Like, if you've actually
logged into the device,
and if you're using an HTML 5
database on your desktop,
you can go find the actual file
in the file system and edit it,
as you might expect.
man: Okay.
Kroeger: Does that answer
your question?
man: So it's stored
in the clear text, or...
Kroeger: Uh, yeah, they are.
man: Okay.
Kroeger: The presumption being
that you can't--
A web application cannot
get access to the database
without being served
from the same domain
as the web application
that created it.
And the browser is
the gatekeeper.
man: Okay. Thank you.
man: Are the domain-based
security mechanism--
Is it related to
single-origin policy?
Kroeger: Yeah, that would be
the right way to say it.
Thank you.
More questions?
Um...
are they appearing here?
[man speaking indistinctly
without microphone]
Kroeger:
I'll repeat the question
for the benefit
of the recording.
Is there a limit
on the amount of data
that can be cached?
And are we caching
to the SD card?
So where the data goes is under
the control of the browser.
We personally don't
control that.
The HTML 5 spec says nothing
of where the browser or platform
should put the data.
It might put it
on the SD card.
in some other kind of store
inside of the device.
Um, on your desktop, it puts it
on your hard disk.
The data volume--
The current iPhone 2.2.1.
hard-limits your database
to five megabytes
per domain.
Um, Gears has a much more
flexible policy
in that we could ask
the Gears database
to be much larger.
And as long as the user
has agreed
in the Gears permission
dialogue,
it could be much larger.
Um, the size of the database
is something that's evolving.
The HTML 5 specification is
sort of fuzzy about
what, exactly, should happen
with database size.
Like, what should the limit be?
They say that there should be
some sort of reasonable default,
and that perhaps the user agent
could ask the user
if they wish it to grow.
And this is how it works
in recent web kit nightlies
and what is supposedly supported
on iPhone 3.0.
man: So how do you foresee
the performance problems
of on-device
or in-browser databases?
Would it make sense
to build--
to invest in making, like,
a JavaScript RM,
or just to wait for
the databases to get faster?
Kroeger: So the database is,
I think--
The database is largely slow,
I believe,
because, um, we're spoiled
by the desktop.
And it's highly not slow
on the desktop.
You know, I--
A flash store on the phone
is not a high-speed
random access storage device
by the standards
of modern SATA disks.
And that's why I think
the database is kinda slow.
But I don't actually--
I don't really know for sure.
man: But is this database
usually SQL Light?
Kroeger: Yeah, it is.
It's SQL Light.
man: So this could be addressed
in SQL Light?
Kroeger: Yeah, that would be--
that would be nice,
I think,
if they sped up SQL Light.
Um, it's fast enough for--
It's fast enough
for caching applications
if you're not relying on it
to be the application model.
man: Okay. Thanks.
man: What's your experience been
with indexing
and, kind of, other,
you know,
more tuning, kind of, tunables
and stuff like that
that you expect from
a SQL implementation?
Kroeger: So indexing is a big--
is a win in SQL Light.
It's not as much of a win
as we'd hoped for.
Um, we got maybe 2x improvement
with indexes.
The performance tools are
difficult to use
on the device itself.
You have to have jail-broken
your phone
and run the SQL Light
command line--
that is, of course,
from the jail-broken website--
on the device to actually
access the database
on the phone itself.
Because the performance results
on the desktop mean nothing.
Everything happens instantly.
Essentially, so...
man: What's the, um--
That's the iPhone story.
What's the similar story
for the Google device?
Their--
Kroeger: The Android?
man: Yeah.
Kroeger: Um...
so once again you have to
run SQL Light on the device.
It's included
in the Android SDK.
It's the same basic idea.
You log into
your Android device,
and you can profile
your database as you see fit.
The Gears implementation...
The actual database interface
in Gears,
perhaps because
it's synchronous,
is faster than
the iPhone implementation.
But the--
Implementing the asynchrony
through a worker
is actually slower
than HTML 5 implementation
of the same thing.
Because in HTML 5, you have
a native thread
running the database.
And then in WSPL,
we have a JavaScript thread
running the synchronous
database.
man: Excellent.
man: Hello. Thank you.
It was very informative.
The question I have is,
the last time I checked,
a custom Android app
did not directly support Gears.
Kroeger: So these are all--
This is a web app, right?
Runs inside of the Android
web browser.
And so the Android web browser
has Gears available.
It's simply a matter of calling
the requisite--
um, recommended code
that is available
from the Gears web site.
And it will put up
a permissions dialogue.
And the user will need
to say yes, that it's okay
for Gears to be available to
this particular web application.
And once that's done,
you can use Gears Calls
in your web app on Android.
man: Okay, and just to,
you know--
whether I got it right.
You know, I know that browsers
on Android
were supporting Gears--
like the browser app.
But if I, say--
I create my own app XYZ...
I mean, my understanding
the last time was
it does not involve Gears.
Or I cannot--
Kroeger: I--I don't know...
man: Okay, thanks.
Kroeger: the answer to that.
man: Um, hi.
Is the API going to evolve
into something like EJB 3?
You know, like Objectory
and that stuff.
Uh, you know, [indistinct].
Kroeger: Which API?
man: The WSPL.
Kroeger: Oh. So the WSPL API
should look very much
like the HTML 5 database API.
If you're thinking that
we could add
some kind of JavaScript
object-relational mapper,
you're right,
and it might happen.
But no promises.
More questions?
man: So what's the Google Gears
roadmap looks like?
Because we have HTML 5 now,
and you guys are going
toward HTML 5, so...
Kroeger: Uh...um...
[laughter]
Yeah, um...
I guess the simple answer,
which isn't really useful,
is that they're converging.
That eventually there will be
one API that is blessed
by the, what...WG working group
that everybody uses.
And people are working very hard
on making that happen.
man: So would you recommend
us using Google Gears
at this point or...?
Kroeger: Well, so one of
the nice things about
this WSPL library is that it
protects you from this choice.
You can write database apps now
against an HTML 5 API.
And they'll work on Gears too.
So that's what we decided
to do.
We had to support Android
and iPhone.
And so, you know,
we built this library
that let us do it.
Um, if you have a need
to support both platforms now,
then I would recommend
you try out our library.
'Cause it will do the job.
And then, as HTML 5 becomes
available natively everywhere,
our library will get skinnier,
and you won't have to change
your code.
man: One further question is
do we have WSPL available
on the desktop?
I guess...on any browser?
Kroeger: It runs in Android
and Chrome and Safari...
correctly.
man: Should be okay.
Thank you.
Kroeger: More questions?
Oh...
Screen sa--
It wants my password.
Yes, it would be really nice
to have an ORM system.
We actually started
writing one
and never really finished it.
The reason why--I mean,
I was writing it.
And the reason why
I abandoned it was that
it wasn't advancing
other features
that were being asked for
by managers.
And it was not, at the time--
We didn't see a good way
to make it
both sufficiently general
and fast.
Um...
it would be--
Hypothetically it would be nice
to have some kind of, um...
compile time tool
that would read a--
say a JSON object definition,
and would construct
the appropriate SQL.
So that's where thoughts are
with doing ORM for JavaScript.
Well, I think we can all
have coffee early
if there's no more questions.
Going once, going twice.
[applause]