Lamm:
Hi, I'm Stephen Lamm,
and I work at Google
in Web Performance.
And today I want to tell you
a little bit
about browser caching
and what you can do
to configure your web pages
so that they're cached properly
in browsers.
And you'll find that,
once you learn it,
it's really easy
to implement it,
and you get a double win,
because not only do your
web pages load more quickly,
but then there's less of a load
on your web servers as well.
Browsers have caches to store
local copies of resources
and web pages because those
resources often do not change
for a long time.
And by storing a local copy,
the browser can avoid having
to make another connection
to the web server and
downloading that resource again.
So now I'd like to show you
a demo
where I'm gonna show you a web
page that has the resources
with all the caching turned off
so that each time
this page is loaded,
the browser has to request
each image in this page.
And then I'm gonna show you
the same page loaded again,
but with the caching headers
turned on.
And you can see the difference
in performance that it has
on the web page.
So here we're loading the page
with the Expires headers
turned off
for all the different resources.
And as you can see, when
the resources are coming in,
they're all coming
from the web server.
Now I'm gonna maximize
the HttpWatch window
so we can look at one image
in particular
and see what
cache control headers it's set.
If you look,
the cache control header is set
so that there is no cache,
so that this item has to be
requested from the server
each time.
The ETag is not set.
And we have an Expires header
that is set in the past.
Now moving on,
we're gonna load the same page,
but this time all the images
are gonna have
the Expires header on.
And so here I type in
the different URL.
I hit Enter.
Now I'm gonna maximize
the HTTP window once again.
I'm gonna click
on an image
to show what the HTTP headers
look like.
So now when we look
at the headers,
we can say that the max-age
is set, it's set in seconds.
And in this case, it works out
to ten years in the future.
There's still no ETag set.
There's also an Expires header.
Now if you set both max-age
and the Expires header,
the max-age header will override
the Expires header.
And finally the Last-Modified
is set,
and it's the same value
before back in 2006.
So now let's load the page
with the Expires on
one more time,
click on the URL bar,
and hit Enter.
And we see that the page loads
much more quickly this time
because it's bringing everything
from cache,
and that's shown here
with HttpWatch
by having everything
in blue.
As you can see, caching can have
a big impact
on the performance
of your web pages.
And it's one
of the easier things to set up.
So thank you for watching,
and for more information,
you can visit
code.google.com/speed.